<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An admonitory letter vvritten by an old minister of the new combinational church, and sent to divers ejected minsters of those parts in which he lives. In which is not boldly and barely affirmed, but also offered fairly to be confirmed by unanswerable arguments. I. The right constitution of a combinational church. II. The corruptions that crept in upon it from the parochial, cathedral, provincial, national, and oecumenical Roman church. III. Who were the heads of these several churches, and what were the qualities of them. Published I. For to inform the ignorant. II. For to reduce the errant.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75899</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A599</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E934_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207674</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866712</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866712</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118996</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75899)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118996)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 140:E934[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An admonitory letter vvritten by an old minister of the new combinational church, and sent to divers ejected minsters of those parts in which he lives. In which is not boldly and barely affirmed, but also offered fairly to be confirmed by unanswerable arguments. I. The right constitution of a combinational church. II. The corruptions that crept in upon it from the parochial, cathedral, provincial, national, and oecumenical Roman church. III. Who were the heads of these several churches, and what were the qualities of them. Published I. For to inform the ignorant. II. For to reduce the errant.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.G. for Richard Lowns, at the White Lion in Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 10."; 8 in imprint date crossed out and "7" written in.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Independent churches --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118996:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118996:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An Admonitory LETTER VVRITTEN By an Old Miniſter of the New Combinational Church, and ſent to divers Ejected Miniſters of thoſe Parts in which he lives.</p>
            <p>IN Which is not boldly and barely affirmed, but alſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered fairly to be confirmed by unanſwerable Arguments,
<list>
                  <item>I. The right conſtitution of a Combinational Church.</item>
                  <item>II. The corruptions that crept in upon it from the Parochial, Cathedral, Provincial, National, and Oecumenical Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church.</item>
                  <item>III. Who were the Heads of theſe ſeveral Churches, and what were the qualities of them.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>PUBLISHED
<list>
                  <item>I. For to inform the Ignorant.</item>
                  <item>II. For to reduce the Errant.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>J. G.</hi> for <hi>Richard Lowns,</hi> at the <hi>White Lion</hi> in <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard, 1658.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:118996:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118996:2"/>
            <head>An Admonitory LETTER VVRITTEN By an Old Miniſter of the New Combinational Church, and ſent to divers Ejected Miniſters of thoſe Parts in which he lives.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat that glorious God who is the giver of all Grace (as well as of every good and perfect gift) would never be weary of conferring on you, or of continuing in you, or yet of encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by you, thoſe real and rich gifts and graces which he (out of his good wil &amp; meer goodneſs) was pleaſed to endue &amp; adorn your precious ſoul withal; for the dayly uſe and exerciſe whereof, his main aim, and uttermoſt end was his own ſervice, and your own ſolace, to heave you up higher
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118996:3"/>in holineſs and happineſs (as I am hopefully perſwaded in my ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heart) then moſt of your Companions or Acquaintance, Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred or Country (and that at the leaſt) by the head and ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; is one of thoſe many motions which I have frequently and unfeignedly found my ſelf moved (and that as I truſt from the higheſt Heavens) for to make unto the Hearer of prayers, and the granter of requeſts:<note place="margin">1. An humble motion for you.</note> this motion is my humble motion for you.</p>
            <p>That you wou'd call to your remembrance, and alſo ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider, and lay to heart, what (I in the judgement of ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal charity am bound to conceive) you cannot chuſe but know, by what Chriſt did reveal to you, and by what you did likewiſe receive from Chriſt; namely, how our God in Covenant hath thought meet to conſtitute three ſeveral ſorts of viſible Churches (and no more to be owned and acknowledged as his) to be foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and found ſucceſſively on earth from the beginning of the world to the end of the ſame: Whereof the firſt was the <hi>Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomical,</hi> or <hi>Domeſtical;</hi> the ſecond was the <hi>National,</hi> or <hi>Judai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal;</hi> and the third was the <hi>Presbyterial</hi> or <hi>Combinational</hi> Church. You your ſelf are not at all any thing ignorant I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that the foremoſt of theſe ſorts did exiſt in, and was confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto thoſe Ages alone, which were before the Moſaical Law, or that the next had its being (and that preciſely) during thoſe very days which were under the force of that Law; either of which ſpaces of time conſiſted of two thouſand years, or neer about: and that the hindermoſt ſort did not begin to be untill after the utter aboliſhment of the ſaid Oeconomical Law. In which third and laſt kind of Church-government, every child of man that is an ingenious child of God, and a conformable mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſt, either really hath for the preſent, or elſe earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly longs and deſires to have for the future, both a name and a nail, according to what is promiſed to the believing Gentiles, and was performed to the believing Jews, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.2. &amp; <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.8. That you would be pleaſed to ſpend ſometimes a few of your ſecond and morning thoughts in the mature peruſing, pondering, and applying of what is thus humbly put before your eyes, and propoſed to your judicious conſideration, is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Motion which I make bold to acquaint you with.<note place="margin">2. An hearty motion to you.</note> This Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is my hearty Motion to you.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118996:3"/>
            <p>That ſome others, eſpecially ſuch of yours whom it may moſt neerly concern, to be well ſeen and skilled therein, may have it made known unto their ſouls by your ſelf (how and where you ſhall ſee cauſe, and think fit) that the firſt viſible Church which was conſtituted by the wiſe builder thereof was a domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Church, being outwardly guided and governed by the firſt born of the family, who were the types and ſhadows of Chriſt Jeſus in the ſeveral houſes of profeſſing Saints; and did conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue from <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Adams</hi> days, to the time of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aarons</hi> pilgrimage in the Wilderneſs of <hi>Sin:</hi> as doth plainly appear to all that deliberately do weigh both what is expreſſed, aad what is neceſſarily implyed in <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.4 compared with <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.17. That the Church of the ſecond ſort was a National Church, conſiſting meerly of Jewiſh perſons, and their Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes for its Members, who were inſtrumentally enlightened and led by the Prieſts and Levites, as their only ordinary Miniſters: the which kind of Church-Government laſted among them from the life of <hi>Moſes</hi> to the death of the <hi>Meſſia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and no longer, as it is exceeding plain and clear to any one that can find in his heart adviſedly to compare the ſeveral teſtimonies of the old and new Teſtament together, which will contribute pregnant light to this particular point; ſuch as are <hi>Exod</hi> 19.6. <hi>Numb.</hi> 8.10. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.7. with <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.9, 10. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.14.17. &amp; <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.12. And that the Church of the laſt and longeſt conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was a Presbyterial, or Combinational Church; whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable opinion and practice (and that without any ground of contradiction in the beſt judgement of unbyaſſed believers) it is, quietly and cordially to ſubject the earthly, erring, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly will of every creature therein, unto the heavenly, infallible, and uncontrolable will of Chriſt; who peremptorily wills and enjoyns all his profeſſed ſubjects, and profeſſing Church-Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to be indoctrinated and diſciplined by the preſcribed mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of thoſe Presbyters (or Teaching and Ruling Elders) that are of their own voluntary Election and regular Ordination, whoſe office-extent reacheth from Chriſts Aſcention, to the Creations Diſſolution: as it is witneſſed by what is written <hi>Acts</hi> 6.5. &amp; 14.23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.7, 8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.8, 28. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.7, 14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.6. &amp; 5.6. &amp; 19.4. That you would reſolve
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118996:4"/>(in his ſtrength whoſe you are, and in whoſe hand your life and whole time alſo is) to reveal and manifeſt unto ſome of yours, ſomewhat (at leaſt) of that much, which the loving and liberal Lord and lender of pounds and Talents, did ſee good to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the care of your conſcience,<note place="margin">3. An harmleſs motion by you.</note> is a third Motion which I was ſtirred up for to ſpread before you. This Motion is my harmleſs Motion by you.</p>
            <p>In caſe that the frequent pondering of this profitable point (which is of ſo much concernment to be throughly verſed in) ſhould puzzle any one that begins for to queſtion how, where, or when did the Chriſtian Church (which at the firſt was Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterial and Pure) become ſo corrupt and polluted, as that ſcarce is the Skeleton, faſhion, or face thereof as much as to be perceived; the more is the pity in moſt places, or (as yet) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt moſt profeſſors of godlineſs. I was really perſwaded that a little pains might prove not only acceptable, but advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious to a perſon that was ſo puzzled about that particular, for to hear and to have it (not alone boldly and barely affirmed, but alſo) fairly and firmly confirmed by unanſwerable argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that it fell to that foul and fearful degeneration (under which it now doth, or ſhould) groan and for which it hath good cauſe to grieve by no fewer then by five diſtinct degrees; whereof the firſt was into a Parochial, the ſecond into a Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral, the third into a Provincial, the fourth into a National, and the fifth was into an Oecumenical, or a Roman Catholique Church.</p>
            <p>The firſt riſe of the rottening of the Church, was its falling from a pure (though poor) Presbyterial Church (which in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of its Primitive conſtitution was compoſed and made up of living ſtones: namely lively Members, and laborious Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, being faſtned and firmly knit unto the Lord Jeſus as their only head by faith, and one to the other by a Fraternal cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of ſervent love; according to the pattern which was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and preſcribed in both Teſtaments. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.5. <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.5. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.37. <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.7, 10, 14. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.13, 19, 22. <hi>Coll.</hi> 2.2, 19. &amp; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5) Into an impure and unpoliſhed Parochial Church at that time, when (ceaſing to elect and ordain either a Teather, a Paſtor, a Ruler, or Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118996:4"/>and Deaconeſs, or Widow) in conformity to the heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Canon, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.7. &amp; 15.4. &amp; 16.1. compared with 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. &amp; <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5, 6.) it was well content to admit and accept of a Parſon, a Vicar, a Warden, an Overſeer of the poor, and a Midwife; by which wiſedom of the fleſh, being no better then enmity againſt God, within a ſhort time after the dayes of the Apoſtles, Chriſts ſpiritual houſe, and growing (as well as li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving) Temple, was turned and transformed into a carnal and dead Town, or apoſtatizing Pariſh, the very beginning and breeding of which Parochial Church is ſeen to have been in the time of <hi>Polycarpus</hi> and <hi>Ireneus,</hi> one of them being an Elder of the Church at <hi>Smyrna,</hi> and a Diſciple of <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt; and the other a Paſtor at <hi>Lyons,</hi> and a Diſciple of that <hi>Polycar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> as any man may eaſily perceive, that will peruſe what is to be obſerved in <hi>Euſetius</hi> his Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, the fourteenth and fifteenth chapters of the fourth Book, with the three and twentieth and four and twentieth of the fifth Book.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond degree of the Combinational Churches corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was the Cathedral Churches generation, which did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to alter and to elevate the places and appellations of the Teacher, Paſtor, Ruler, and Deacon, into thoſe unſcripture-like titles of Lord Biſhop, Dean, Chancellor, and Arch Deacon, who ventured to uſurp the Power of excommunication againſt the Members and Miniſters of many congregations in their Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods and Councils, contrary to what was practiced in that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Pattern, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.24. which is laid down, and left as well for the imitation as information of after-Ages; whoſe work it was by Scripture-proofs to confute ſouls-ſubverting po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, and to confirm Chriſtian Doctrines, without uſing any manner of authority to cenſure any mans perſon, being that that is the expreſſe priviledge of the Presbyterial Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4, 5. &amp; 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.15. The Babe-age of which u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation is made mention of (as newly appearing in the world) by what was exerciſed by <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> againſt <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> of <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> as well as againſt <hi>Arrius</hi> in the reign of <hi>Conſtantius</hi> and <hi>Conſtance</hi> the ſons of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperor; as 'tis to be ſeen in <hi>Socrates Scholaſticus,</hi> the ſecond book, the third chapter, compared with the two and thirtieth chapter of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118996:5"/>the ſecond Book, or <hi>Evag.</hi> the ſixth chapter of the firſt Book.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third degree of the Presbyterial Churches degeneration was its climbing up to the ſtyle of a Provincial Church, whoſe Paſtor was not afraid nor aſhamed to aſſume the name and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Arch Biſhop, and Metropolitan, leaving the ſervile and ſubſervient titles of Prebend, Surrogate, and Vicar general, as terms good enough to the inferiour officers his underlings: of which proud and profane Peſt-houſe that <hi>Auſtin</hi> (who was ſent from <hi>Gregory</hi> the laſt of good Biſhops, and the firſt of the evil Popes of <hi>Rome</hi>) is reputed and recorded to have been the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Founder in this land, even then, when he was both ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fly and ſtoutly oppoſed by the Monks of <hi>Bangor</hi> in the year of our Lord 596. and in the reign of King <hi>Ethelbert;</hi> witneſs <hi>Fox</hi> his <hi>Martyrology</hi> page 119. together with the reſt of the Engliſh Hiſtorians, and <hi>Evagrius lib.</hi> 2.8.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth famous degree of the Combinational Churches infamous defection was its notable naughty inlarging its ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a National Church, when, and whence (without coutrover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie) aroſe that Jewiſh imitation, and irregularly religious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of five frivolous and foundationleſs cuſtoms and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, of which, the firſt was of National times, as the fiſty years feſtivals, or holy working dayes, Curſed-maſs, Candle-maſs. The ſecond, was of National places, as the conſecrated Meeting houſes, Porches, Chancels, and Church-yards. The third was of National perſons, as the Univerſal Preachers, Office-Prieſts, and Half Prieſts, or Dioceſian-Deacons. The fourth was of National pious performances, as ſtinted Worſhip, Choriſters, ſinging of Pſalms, with all the Rubrique poſtures. And the fifth was of National payments, or ſpiritual profits, as Offerings, Tithes, and Mortuaries. All which faithleſs and fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtical faſhions were the illegitimate legal off-ſpring of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Parliaments in this and the neighbour Nations; witneſs the publique Acts, Statutes, and other Ordinances in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The fifth and higheſt degree of Church-deformity is the Oecumenical Church, otherwiſe called Roman Catholike; the which in the apprehenſion of I know not how many Kingdoms
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118996:5"/>is the very beſt, though in the judgement of Chriſt Jeſus in the Scriptures it is the very baſeſt, becauſe the beaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt, and the moſt blaſphemous of all the Baſtard-Church conſtitutions, that ever were till now; witneſs what is written, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.1, 3, 5, 6. Whoſe Paſtors and other Presbyters, yea (ſin-pardoning Pope, Cardinals, Abbots, with others were owned and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged for to be, and thereby not a few (if not of the ſummon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Councels; yet) in ſeveral Synods in ſundry countries, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that Churches abominable iniquities were ſo encreaſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their heads, and their trayterous treſpaſſes were ſo egregiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grown up to heaven, as that the long-forbearing Lord could no longer forbear, but was put upon it, and as it were neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated for to take vengeance on their inventions, as on <hi>Aarons</hi> golden calfe, and <hi>Samuels</hi> grievous connivency at the evils of his ſons ſpoken of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 99.6.8.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>Much reſpected Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MAy not any one to whoſe Inwards the knowledge of theſe particulars is come, ingeniouſly confeſs that his very ſoul is clearly convinced of the mighty and manifold corruptions which have crept into, are cheriſht within, and conteſted about by many (yea, by too too many) Chriſtians of too too many Churches? And may not I (though a ſtranger to my neereſt friends, becauſe an exile newly arrived to the land of my nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity) ſafely appeal to any perſon that hath either conſcience, or common ſenſe, whether Chriſt Jeſus our ſupreme Lord Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, upon whoſe ſhoulders the government of the Churches is laid, hath not of late years borne a loud witneſs againſt every one of thoſe five afore mentioned kinds of deformed Churches, and that in thoſe very countries which are counted and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called Chriſtendom? If ſo, God forbid, that there ſhould be any Chriſtian man (and more eſpecially any Clergy man) ſo carnal, and ſo careleſs in all theſe coaſts, as not to be both able and willing to conceive and conclude himſelf to be called upon for to conſider of, and to lay to heart, the great and grievous deſolations which his hand hath made amongſt the moſt and mightieſt of the ſons of men.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, hath not the long provoked Lord begun in this Iſland
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118996:6"/>and in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to pull down loweſt, that looſe, that lofty and lawleſs Church, which the corrupt Clergy had lifted up higheſt? namely, the Oecumenical, or Roman Catholike Church, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the ſin-pardoning, or rather ſoul-poyſoning Pope was the vile and virulent head, who was therefore, and upon that account, publickly declared, and generally (though not univerſally) belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be a very horrible Monſter, as well as a very abominable beaſt, becauſe of its ten horns; witneſs what is written, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.3, 5.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Hath not Chriſt hid his face from, and bent his brow againſt the National Church, as being the very next in naughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? whereof the Britiſh King was (although not an invincible) yet a violent head, which was therefore the leſs victorious, and more vincible; partly becauſe the head (not only of a very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canonical, but alſo) of a very unſpiritual corporation: and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe of the ſaid National corporations inconſiſtency with the Scripture precepts, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. &amp; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.23.) which do require its ordinary congregating in one place, ſeconded and aggravated by its notorio us inconformity to the Scripture pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns. (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.16, 22. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.5) where the Chriſtian Combinational Church is called (not a whole Nation, but) a holy City, a growing Temple, a ſpiritual Houſe, or a fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enlightning, and a ſoul-enlivening Church, gathered, built, fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, cul'd and called out, of and from a carnal and crooked Nation, which was both dark and darkneſs it ſelf; witneſſe what is written, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.3.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, Did not Chriſts own mouth marvellouſly condemn the prevailing corruptions of the Provincial Church, whereof the chief Prelate or Arch Biſhop was the haughty and horrible head: which was therefore ſo much the more abſurd, and bold head, becauſe of its baſe and blaſphemous blindneſs, in daring to take up and aſcribe to its ſelf ſuch a ſtyle &amp; title as is not commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicable to any creature, but is proper and peculiar to Chriſts own ſacred perſon, being that beſides himſelf none can be ſafely ſaid to be an Arch-Biſhop, or Chief-ſhepherd; If one of the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenteſt Apoſtles may be believed, whoſe words imply no leſs, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.4. When the chief Shepherd ſhall appear, ye ſhall receive an incorruptible crown of Glory. Who was that Church-Miniſter?
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118996:6"/>what was his name, or where did he dwell? who came once into a capacity to be accounted ſuch a ſuperlative Counſellor, or comforter, as was endued either with ability, or authority to confer a ſpiritual crown on any one of the ſincere Elders of a Church of Saints? which is ſuch a matter as a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſon of man ſhould not dare to hear (much leſs to make) any mention of, without ſome meaſure of amazement in his very ſoul.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, was it not Chriſts own hand that did pour out a dreadful Vial of viſible vengeance upon the Cathedral Church, whereof the lordly Dioceſan was (not ſo much the Idle as) the Addle head, which (therefore, and under that notion) was not venerable, nor tolerable, becauſe of its direct and point blank oppoſition unto divers, and down right peremptory prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, at <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.26. Ye know that the Lords of the Gentiles exerciſe domination over them, but it ſhall not be ſo among you. And 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. <hi>feed the flock of God which depends upon you, not as though you were Lords ever Gods heritage.</hi> Which roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Laws do teſtifie all ſuch lofty Lords, and Lordleſs out-lawes to be ſuch illegal and irregular livers, as that their unhallowed dwellings appear to be long ſince deſtined and appointed for Hedge-Hogs to houſe and harbour at; yea, for <hi>Jim</hi> and <hi>Ohim</hi> with the wild Satyrs to dance in, and for Owles and Vultures to dung on, being afraid of none to drive them away. Thus veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying that terrible threat to be performed and fulfilled at length, which was propheſied of old; witneſs what is written in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13.19.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, and finally, was it not Chriſts own foot that hath kicked at, and caſt contempt (and that not a little) upon thoſe evil favoured and condemned Churches, which are yet ſtanding in many Countreys, though they are remarkably reeling and ready for to fall? Is it not Chriſts own voice that is at this time, and in moſt places audibly pleading his own cauſe againſt the Parochial Church? whereof the preaching Parſon (being it muſt not be denied that divers of the pariſh Parſons are not any preaching Parſons, witneſs all the oppreſſing Impropriators) is openly ſeen to ſtand upon his trial, as the odd and eldeſt evil head. And though this head be the laſt head, and did the leaſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118996:7"/>hurt of all the other heads, yet the Almighty Lord hath (as yet) lift up his hand againſt him: yet at this time 'tis his turn to lie down under the laſh, and like the luke-warm Angel of <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cea</hi> (by taking ſhame and confuſion of face unto himſelfe) to receive whatſoever ſharp correction ſhall (as a cordial of love) be adminiſtred unto him, for the preventing of the ſpewing of his name out of Chriſts mouth, as is manifeſt from what is foretold, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.19. therefore the whole (half blind Political body of the Pariſh Church) doth openly appear to be, though not utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uncurable, yet in reſpect of its preſent poſture in its numerous abominations, altogether unapproveable, becauſe of its rejecting the commandments of God, that it may obſerve the traditions of men. Againſt which hateful offence Jeſus Chriſt doth ſadly complain, <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k</hi> 7.7, 9. and concerning which offenſive ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, Chriſts ſincere ſervant doth ſeriouſly caution, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.8, 18. Beware left there be any man that ſpoil you through Philoſophy and vain deceit, through the traditions of men, according to the rudiments of the world, and not after Chriſt. Let no man at his pleaſure bear rule over you by humbleneſs of mind, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which holy watch-words and wholſom warnings (had they been heedfully hearkened unto by all ſuch as were Church-officers) would without queſtion have reſtrained the multitude of Church-hearers from many ſuch obſervations and alterations as muſt of neceſſity be either amended timely, or mourned for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally; witneſs what is written, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.9, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If there were nothing amiſs (or out of order) to be obſerved in the pariſh meeting-houſes, if there were never ſo full freedom from Communion, Book-praying, and from Homily Book prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, as well as from Common-book-ſwearing; if all bare Heads were barr'd out from their places, and utterly rejected from ever being any ſpiritual Overſeers again afore they were inwardly qualified by Chriſts ſin-crucifying, and ſoul quickning ſpirit in a cleanſed conſcience, and alſo outwardly, and orderly called by Chriſts covenant-ſervants in a cleanſed Combinational Church, if there were an unanimous rooting down of all double reading (I mean that babling reading of two chapters, which is not ſeconded with the opening and expounding of the ſame, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it cannot but be confeſſed that 'twas ſuch a courſe as was
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118996:7"/>quite contrary to what is commanded and commended in the Scriptures of truth, as all do well know that are acquainted with what is written, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.2. <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h.</hi> 8.8 <hi>Luke</hi> 4.16. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.15. &amp; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.23, 24. If there were no news amongſt them of one Relique of all the Romiſh Rites, or other humane Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as Matrimonial Bonds, Marriage Ring, Sign of the Croſs, White Surplice, Choriſters ſinging. Funeral Sermons, Idol Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, of God-fathers and God-mothers or groundleſs applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of publick or private Baptiſm unto the Infants of prophane Parents; and if none but Chriſts own faithful friends and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers were admitted to be fed, or phyſicked at his Supper-feaſt; yet the meer ſight of a Monarchical Pew to ſtand in the ſtead of a Miniſterial Pulpit, is a ſtrong plea of a ſtrange Apoſtaſie from the commendable practice of the primitive Chriſtians; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſuch a coop is not of a ſufficient capacity to contain (at once) any more perſons then one. Whereas it is of moral equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, (and conſequently of perpetual obſervation) that a rightly reformed Presbyterial Church ſhould have all her Elders (who are engaged by vertue of their office to begin and end all the publick Ordinances, and to tranſact all the open concernments of the City of God) for to ſtand and ſit together in the face and full view of the whole Aſſembly, and by ſo much the more, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are ſo plainly warranted, and ſo punctually preſcribed as they be, both to wait, and to walk according to the patterns ſhewed in the mount; witneſs, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.42. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.44. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.5. and as in all other points, ſo in this particular concerning the Elders Pulpit, they are tied and limited by their commiſſion, to hold conformity with what is upon ſacred Record, as this is (and that not only neceſſarily implyed, but) eminently expreſſed in ſeveral Scripture-expreſſions, as <hi>Neh.</hi> 8.4. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.11. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.6. &amp; 5.6. &amp; 19.4.</p>
            <p>To ſum up in ſhort the whole ſumme and ſubſtance of what I would ſhew until ſuch times as the Parochial Churches of the Nations do again become truely Presbyterial, and ſo reformed in their eſſential parts, conſiſting of viſible converts, and an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite covenant, which are the matter and form of a Church; witneſs, <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.5. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.37. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.5. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.47. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.1. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. &amp; 9.13.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:118996:8"/>
            <p>And until they be alſo refined in their Integral parts, which are the Organs or Officers thereof, that as Eyes, Mouth, Hands, are to ſee, ſpeak, and act in their behalf, until they both deſire and endeavour to be endowed, firſt with a Teacher to diſpenſe the word of knowledge and information to the judgement. Secondly, with a Paſtor to diſpenſe the word of wiſedom and exhortation to the will and affections. Thirdly, with a Ruler to diſpence the word of rebuke and admonition to the irregular in life and converſation. And fourthly, with Deacons and Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows to receive and diſpence the weekly contribution, that is belonging, and alſo brought to the King of Saints from his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in covenant, toward the maintainance of the table of the Lord, the table of the Church Elders, and the tables of ſuch of the fellow-members as be in lack; and all this in obedience to what is enjoyned in his revealed will; namely, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2, 7, 8. &amp; 16.1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.8.28. &amp; 16.1, 2. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. &amp; 5.10, 20. Until that I ſay the Parochial Churches be thus qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified: can you upon good ground expect (as to them) either the manifeſtation of ſure mercy, or the enjoyment of ſolid peace? knowing that comminations are properly appertaining to vile and violent ſin-loving ſinners; as 'tis ſhew'd by the Oracles of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.5, 6. and Rev. 14.10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22.15. And that Church-promiſes and Church-priviledges, as well as Chriſts conſolations, are peculiarly applicable to ſuch covenant-makers with God and Men (as through the ſtrength of their ſurety) are covenant keepers with both; which covenant-making, and covenant breaking is expreſſed and perceived by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular walking towards them that are without, as well as towards them that are within; according to what is written, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. &amp; 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. If you can tell any ſuch tidings as a heavenly promiſe to unheavenly perſons, or a holy priviledge to the ſouls, or the ſeed of unholy Parents, that you would find in your heart to give me ſome notice thereof, and to acquaint me with any one of thoſe good grounds of any lively hope that they will be everlaſtingly happy, is the laſt of thoſe Motions which I make bold for to leave with you to conſider of, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118996:8"/>upon. This Motion is my heavenly Motion for my ſelfe, the granting of which, will engage me (yet far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) to be, to remain, and alſo to acknowledge my ſelfe,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your thankful Remembrancer in his neareſt approaches to the Throne of Grace.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
